I am very, very happy to be amidst some of the most --
انا سعيد جداً جداً ﻷن أكون بين بعض من معظم --
the lights are really disturbing my eyes
حقيقة الأضواء تتوزع على عيناي
and they're reflecting on my glasses.
وتنعكس على نظارتي.
I am very happy and honored to be amidst
أنا سعيدُ جداً ومُشرَف ﻷكون بين
very, very innovative and intelligent people.
أناس أذكياء جداً جداً.
I have listened to the three previous speakers,
،لقد أستمعت إلى المتحدثين الثلاثة السابقين
and guess what happened?
وخمنوا ماذا حدث؟
Every single thing I planned to say, they have said it here,
،اي شئ خططت ﻷن أذكره، ذكروه هُم هُنا
and it looks and sounds like I have nothing else to say.
.ويبدو أنه كأنما لا يوجد شئ لأذكره
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there is a saying in my culture
لكنهم في ثقافتنا يقولون
that if a bud leaves a tree without saying something,
،لو أن هنالك برعم غادر الشجرة دون أن يقول شيئاً
that bud is a young one.
هذا البرعم هو أصغرهم.
So, I will -- since I am not young and am very old,
لذلك -- وﻷنني لست صغير وأنا كبير جداً
I still will say something.
.سأقول شيئاً
We are hosting this conference at a very opportune moment,
نحن نستضيف هذا المؤتمر في وقت مناسب
because another conference is taking place in Berlin.
ﻷن هنالك مؤتمر آخر ينعقد في برلين
It is the G8 Summit.
.إنه مؤتمر قمة دول مجموعة الثمانية الصناعية الكبرى
The G8 Summit proposes that the solution to Africa's problems
وهذا المؤتمر يقترح حلول لمشاكل أفريقيا
should be a massive increase in aid,
،بأن يكون هنالك زيادة في المعونة
something akin to the Marshall Plan.
أو هذا حسب خطة مارشال.
Unfortunately, I personally do not believe in the Marshall Plan.
وللأسف، انا شخصياً لا أؤمن بخطة مارشال.
One, because the benefits of the Marshall Plan have been overstated.
واحد، ﻷن فوائد خطة مارشال مبالغ فيه.
Its largest recipients were Germany and France,
إن أكبر المستلمين هُم ألمانيا وفرنسا،
and it was only 2.5 percent of their GDP.
وإنها فقط 2.5 في المائة من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي
An average African country receives foreign aid
وكبلد أفريقي متوسط يستقبل معونة خارجية
to the tune of 13, 15 percent of its GDP,
بالضبط 13 أو 15 بالمائة من ناتجها المحلي الإجمالي،
and that is an unprecedented transfer of financial resources
وذلك تحويل لم يسبق له مثيل في الموارد المالية
from rich countries to poor countries.
من الدول الغنية للدول الفقيرة.
But I want to say that there are two things we need to connect.
لكني أريد أن أقول أن هنالك شيئين نريد أن نربطهم.
How the media covers Africa in the West, and the consequences of that.
كيف تغطي وسائل الإعلام أفريقيا في الغرب، وما يترتب على ذلك.
By displaying despair, helplessness and hopelessness,
،بعرض البؤس، والعجز واليأس
the media is telling the truth about Africa, and nothing but the truth.
الإعلام ينقل الحقيقة عن أفريقيا، ولا شئ غيرها.
However, the media is not telling us the whole truth.
لكن، الإعلام لا ينقل لنا الحقيقة كاملة
Because despair, civil war, hunger and famine,
ﻷن البؤس، والحرب الأهلية، والجوع والمجاعات،
although they're part and parcel of our African reality,
على الرغم من أنهم جزء لا يتجزأ من واقعنا الأفريقي،
they are not the only reality.
إنهم ليس الواقع الوحيد.
And secondly, they are the smallest reality.
وثانياً، إنهم أصغر جزء من واقعنا.
Africa has 53 nations.
أفريقيا لديها 53 دولة.
We have civil wars only in six countries,
لدينا حروب أهلية فقط في 6 دول،
which means that the media are covering only six countries.
وهذا ما يعني أن الإعلام يغطي فقط 6 دول.
Africa has immense opportunities that never navigate
أفريقيا لديها فرص هائلة لم تنقل
through the web of despair and helplessness
عبر الإنترنت من البؤس واليأس
that the Western media largely presents to its audience.
والذي يقدمه الإعلام الغربي لجمهوره الكبير.
But the effect of that presentation is, it appeals to sympathy.
ولكن تأثير هذا العرض هو أن يناشد التعاطف
It appeals to pity. It appeals to something called charity.
يناشد الشفقة؛ يناشد لشئ يُدعى الصدقة.
And, as a consequence, the Western view
ونتيجة لذلك، النظرة الغربية
of Africa's economic dilemma is framed wrongly.
لمعضلة الإقتصاد الأفريقي مؤطرة تأطير خاطئ.
The wrong framing is a product of thinking
الخطأ المؤطر هو ناتج من
that Africa is a place of despair.
أن أفريقيا هي مكان للبأس.
What should we do with it? We should give food to the hungry.
ماذا نفعل معها؟ علينا أن نعطي الطعام للجوعى.
We should deliver medicines to those who are ill.
علينا إعطاء الأدوية للمرضى.
We should send peacekeeping troops
علينا إرسال قوات حفظ السلام
to serve those who are facing a civil war.
ليخدموا من يواجهون حرباً أهلية.
And in the process, Africa has been stripped of self-initiative.
وفي هذه العملية تُجرد أفريقيا من المبادرة الذاتية.
I want to say that it is important to recognize
أريد أن أقول أن المُهم هو الإعتراف
that Africa has fundamental weaknesses.
بأن لأفريقيا نقاط ضعف أساسية.
But equally, it has opportunities and a lot of potential.
ولكن بالمثل، لديها كثير من الفرص المحتملة.
We need to reframe the challenge that is facing Africa,
نُريد إعادة تأطير التحديات التي تواجه أفريقيا
from a challenge of despair,
من تحديات البؤس،
which is called poverty reduction,
البؤس الذي يُدعى الحد من الفقر،
to a challenge of hope.
إلى تحديات الأمل.
We frame it as a challenge of hope, and that is worth creation.
نؤطرها في تحديات الأمل، وهذا هو الصنيع الجيَد.
The challenge facing all those who are interested in Africa
التحدي الذي يواجه كل المهتمين بأفريقيا
is not the challenge of reducing poverty.
ليس هو تحدي الحد من الفقر.
It should be a challenge of creating wealth.
يجب أن يكون هو تحدي إنشاء الثروة.
Once we change those two things --
عندما نُغير هذين الشيئين --
if you say the Africans are poor and they need poverty reduction,
إذا كُنت تقول أن الأفارقة فُقراء ويحتاجون للدعم من الفقر
you have the international cartel of good intentions
لديك كارتل عالمي للنوايا الحسنة
moving onto the continent, with what?
للإنتقال للقارة، مع ماذا؟
Medicines for the poor, food relief for those who are hungry,
أدوية للفقراء، وطعام إغاثة للجوعى،
and peacekeepers for those who are facing civil war.
وقوات حفظ السلام لمن يواجهون حرباً أهلية.
And in the process, none of these things really are productive
وهذه العملية حقيقة لا شئ فيها مُثمر
because you are treating the symptoms, not the causes
ﻷنك تعالج الأعراض، وليس الأسباب
of Africa's fundamental problems.
المشاكل أفريقيا الأساسية.
Sending somebody to school and giving them medicines,
إرسال أحدهم للمدرسة وإعطاءه الأدوية،
ladies and gentlemen, does not create wealth for them.
سيادتي وسادتي، لا يجعله ثرياً.
Wealth is a function of income, and income comes from you finding
الثروة هي وظيفة الدخل، والدخل يأتي بإيجاد
a profitable trading opportunity or a well-paying job.
فرص تجارة مربحة أو إيجاد عمل بمرتب عالي.
Now, once we begin to talk about wealth creation in Africa,
الآن، عندما نبدأ بالتحدث عن خلق الثروة في أفريقيا،
our second challenge will be,
التحدي الثاني لنا سيكون،
who are the wealth-creating agents in any society?
من هُم وكلاء خلق الثروة في أي مجتمع؟
They are entrepreneurs. [Unclear] told us they are always
هم رجال الأعمال. [غير واضح] قالوا لنا انهم دائما
about four percent of the population, but 16 percent are imitators.
حوالي 4 بالمائة من التعداد السكاني، ولكن 16 بالمائة ضُعفاء.،
But they also succeed at the job of entrepreneurship.
لكنهم أيضاً ينجحون في عمل روح المبادرة.
So, where should we be putting the money?
إذاً إين علينا أن نضع المال؟
We need to put money where it can productively grow.
نحتاج أن نضع المال في مكان ينمو فيه ويُثمر.
Support private investment in Africa, both domestic and foreign.
دعم الإستثمارات الخاصة في أفريقيا، المحلية والأجنبية.
Support research institutions,
دعم مؤسسات البحث،
because knowledge is an important part of wealth creation.
ﻷن المعرفة جزء مهم من خلق الثروة.
But what is the international aid community doing with Africa today?
لكن ماذا يفعل مجتمع المانحين الدولي في أفريقيا؟
They are throwing large sums of money for primary health,
إنهم يرمون بمبالغ كبيرة للصحة الأولية،
for primary education, for food relief.
للتعليم الإبتدائي، ولأطعمة الإغاثة.
The entire continent has been turned into
القارة بأكلمها تحولت إلى
a place of despair, in need of charity.
مكان للبؤس، وتحتاج للإغاثة.
Ladies and gentlemen, can any one of you tell me
سيداتي وسادتي، هل يمكن لأي أحد منكم أن يخبرني
a neighbor, a friend, a relative that you know,
جار أو صديق أو قريب يعرفه،
who became rich by receiving charity?
أصبح غنياً عن طريق الإغاثة؟
By holding the begging bowl and receiving alms?
من خلال عقد الاستجداء وتلقي الصدقات؟
Does any one of you in the audience have that person?
هل هناك أي واحد من الحضور لديه هذا الشخص؟
Does any one of you know a country that developed because of
هل يعرف أي أحد منكم دولة تقدمت بسبب
the generosity and kindness of another?
الكرم والعطف من الآخر؟
Well, since I'm not seeing the hand,
حسناً، بما أنني لا أري أي يد،
it appears that what I'm stating is true.
هذا يعني أن ما أفيده صحيحاً.
(Bono: Yes!)
المُشارك: نعم!
Andrew Mwenda: I can see Bono says he knows the country.
أنردو مويندا: أرى مُشارك يقول أن يعرف دولة.
Which country is that?
ما هي تلك الدولة؟
(Bono: It's an Irish land.)
بونو: إنه إسم إيرلندي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Bono: [unclear])
بونو : [غير واضح]
AM: Thank you very much. But let me tell you this.
شكراً جزيلاً لك، لكن دعني أخبرك بهذا.
External actors can only present to you an opportunity.
العوامل الخارجية يمكنها أن تقدم لك فرصة فقط.
The ability to utilize that opportunity and turn it into an advantage
القدرة على الاستفادة من هذه الفرصة وتحويلها إلى ميزة
depends on your internal capacity.
تعتمد على سعتك الداخلية.
Africa has received many opportunities.
أفريقيا تستقبل كثير من الفرص،
Many of them we haven't benefited much.
وكثير من هذه الفرص لم يُستفاد منها حتى الآن.
Why? Because we lack the internal, institutional framework
لماذا؟ لأننا نفتقر للإطار المؤسسي الداخلي
and policy framework that can make it possible for us
والإطار السياسي الذي يُمكن أن يجعل ذلك ممكناً
to benefit from our external relations. I'll give you an example.
أن نستفيد من العلاقات الخارجية. سأعطيك مثالاُ.
Under the Cotonou Agreement,
،بموجب اتفاقية كوتونو
formerly known as the Lome Convention,
كانت تعرف سابقا باسم اتفاقية لومي،
African countries have been given an opportunity by Europe
الدول الأفريقي مُنحت فُرص من أوروبا
to export goods, duty-free, to the European Union market.
لتصدير البضائع، تم إعفاءها من الرسوم الجمركية، إلى سوق الاتحاد الأوروبي.
My own country, Uganda, has a quota to export 50,000 metric tons
مدينتي، يوغندا لديها حصص لتصدير 50،000 طن متري،
of sugar to the European Union market.
من السكر لسوق الإتحاد الأوروبي.
We haven't exported one kilogram yet.
ونحن لم نُصدر حتى واحد كيلو إلى الآن.
We import 50,000 metric tons of sugar from Brazil and Cuba.
نحن نستورد 50،000 طن متري من السكر من البرازيل وكوبا.
Secondly, under the beef protocol of that agreement,
ثانياً على حسب بروتوكل لحم البقر من تلك الأتفاقية،
African countries that produce beef
الدول الأفريقي التي تنتج اللحم البقري
have quotas to export beef duty-free to the European Union market.
لديها حصص لتصدير اللحم البقري، بدون رسوم جمارك، إلى سوق الإتحاد الأوروبي.
None of those countries, including Africa's most successful nation, Botswana,
ولا واحدة من هذه الدول، بما في ذلك الدول الأكثر نجاحاً، بتسوانا
has ever met its quota.
قد جمعت حصتها.
So, I want to argue today that the fundamental source of Africa's
لذلك أريد أن أجادل اليوم أن المصادر الأساسية لأفريقيا
inability to engage the rest of the world
عدم القدرة على الإنخراط في بقية العالم
in a more productive relationship
في أكثر العلاقات البناءة
is because it has a poor institutional and policy framework.
وذلك ﻷنها لديها مؤسسية فقيرة وكذلك إطارها السياسي.
And all forms of intervention need support,
وكل أنواع التدخل تحتاج لدعم،
the evolution of the kinds of institutions that create wealth,
تطور بعض المؤسسات التي تصنع الثروة،
the kinds of institutions that increase productivity.
تطور المؤسسات التي تزيد الإنتاجية.
How do we begin to do that, and why is aid the bad instrument?
كيف نبدأ في فعل ذلك ولماذا المعونة هي الوسيلة الأسوأ؟
Aid is the bad instrument, and do you know why?
المعونة هي الوسيلة الأسوأ، وأنتم تعرفون لماذا؟
Because all governments across the world need money to survive.
لأن كل الحكومات على وجه الأرض تحتاج للمال لتبقى على قيد الحياة.
Money is needed for a simple thing like keeping law and order.
هناك حاجة للأموال لشئ بسيط كحفظ القانون والنظام.
You have to pay the army and the police to show law and order.
عليك أن تدفع للجيش والشرطة لتظهر القانون والنظام.
And because many of our governments are quite dictatorial,
وﻷن حكوماتنا جميعها دكتاتورية تماماً،
they need really to have the army clobber the opposition.
عليهم إمتلاك الجيش لهزم المعارضة.
The second thing you need to do is pay your political hangers-on.
الشئ الثاني الذي تحتاجه أن تدفع للسياسيين المتطفلين.
Why should people support their government?
لماذا يتعين على الناس دعم حكومتهم؟
Well, because it gives them good, paying jobs,
حسناً، ﻷنها تعطيهم وظائف ذات رواتب جيدة.
or, in many African countries, unofficial opportunities
أو، في العديد من الدول الأفريقية، الفرص الغير مضمونة
to profit from corruption.
للإستفادة من الفساد.
The fact is no government in the world,
الحقيقة هي، أنه لا توجد دولة في العالم،
with the exception of a few, like that of Idi Amin,
بإستثناء عدد قليل مثل عيدي أمين،
can seek to depend entirely on force as an instrument of rule.
يمكن أن تسعى إلى أن تعتمد اعتمادا كليا على القوة كأداة للحكم.
Many countries in the [unclear], they need legitimacy.
كثير من الدول في [غير واضح]، يحتاجون لشرعية.
To get legitimacy, governments often need to deliver things like primary education,
للحصول على الشرعية، تحتاج الحكومات عادة لتحرير أشياء مثل التعليم الإبتدائي،
primary health, roads, build hospitals and clinics.
الصحة الأولية، الطرق، بناء المستشفيات والعيادات.
If the government's fiscal survival
إذا كان بقاء الحكومة المالية
depends on it having to raise money from its own people,
يعتمد على جمع المال من شعبها،
such a government is driven by self-interest
مثل هذه الحكومة يقودها دافع المصلحة الذاتية
to govern in a more enlightened fashion.
لتحكم بطريقة أكثر استنارة.
It will sit with those who create wealth.
ستجلس مع أولئك الذين صنعوا ثروة.
Talk to them about the kind of policies and institutions
تُحدثهم عن مختلف السياسيات والمؤسسات.
that are necessary for them to expand a scale and scope of business
والذي هو ضرورة لهم لتوسيع حجم ونطاق أعمالهم
so that it can collect more tax revenues from them.
حتى تتمكن من جميع عائدات الضرائب منهم.
The problem with the African continent
مشكلة القارة الأفريقية
and the problem with the aid industry
ومشكلة صناعة المعونة
is that it has distorted the structure of incentives
هو أنه قد تشوه هيكل الحوافز
facing the governments in Africa.
التي تواجه الحكومات في أفريقيا.
The productive margin in our governments' search for revenue
على هامش الإنتاجية في حكومتنا البحث عن الإيرادات
does not lie in the domestic economy,
لا يعتمد على الإقتصاد المحلي،
it lies with international donors.
إنه يعتمد على المانحين العالميين.
Rather than sit with Ugandan --
بدلا من الجلوس مع اليوغنديين --
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)
rather than sit with Ugandan entrepreneurs,
بدلاً من الجلوس مع رجال الأعمال اليوغنديين،
Ghanaian businessmen, South African enterprising leaders,
رجال الأعمال في غانا، قُواد رجال الأعمال الجنوب أفريقيين،
our governments find it more productive
حكومتنا تجدها أكثر إنتاجية
to talk to the IMF and the World Bank.
للتحدث مع صندوق النقد الدولي والبنك العالمي.
I can tell you, even if you have ten Ph.Ds.,
يمكنني أن أقول لكم، حتى لو كان عند 10 درجات دكتوراة،
you can never beat Bill Gates in understanding the computer industry.
لا يمكنك التفوق على بيل جيتس في فهم صناعة الكمبيوتر.
Why? Because the knowledge that is required for you to understand
لماذا؟ ﻷن المعرفة هي المطلوبة لتفهم
the incentives necessary to expand a business --
والتي تلزمك لتحفزك لتوسيع أعمالك،
it requires that you listen to the people, the private sector actors in that industry.
يتطلب عليك الإسمتاع إلى أشخاص، ممثلي القطاع الخاص في تلك الصناعة.
Governments in Africa have therefore been given an opportunity,
الحكومات الأفريقية تم منحها فرصة
by the international community, to avoid building
بواسطة المجمتع الدولي لتجنب إقامة
productive arrangements with your own citizens,
ترتيبات مثمرة مع مواطنيها،
and therefore allowed to begin endless negotiations with the IMF
وبالتالي سُمح لها بالبدء في مفاوضات لا نهاية لها مع صندوق النقد الدولي
and the World Bank, and then it is the IMF and the World Bank
والبنك الدولي، ومن ثم إنهم صندوق النقد الدولي والبنك الدولي
that tell them what its citizens need.
هُم الذين يخبرونهم عن حوجة مواطنيهم.
In the process, we, the African people, have been sidelined
نحن في هذه العملية، والشعوب الافريقية، قد تم تهميشها
from the policy-making, policy-orientation, and policy-
من صنع السياسات، وتوجيه السياسة، وسياسة
implementation process in our countries.
تنفيذ عملية في بلداننا.
We have limited input, because he who pays the piper calls the tune.
لدينا مساهمة محدودة ، لأنه هو من يدفع للزمار الذي يعزف النغمات.
The IMF, the World Bank, and the cartel of good intentions in the world
صندوق النقد الدولي، البنك الدولي، وكارتل النوايا الحسنة في العالم،
has taken over our rights as citizens,
فاقت حقوقنا كمواطنين،
and therefore what our governments are doing, because they depend on aid,
وهنالك أيضاً ما تفعله حكومتنا، ﻷنها تعتمد على المعونة،
is to listen to international creditors rather than their own citizens.
أن تستمع إلى المانحيين الدوليين بدلاً عن مواطنيها.
But I want to put a caveat on my argument,
ولكنني أريد أن أضع التحذير على حُجتي،
and that caveat is that it is not true that aid is always destructive.
وذلك التحذير أنه ليس صحيحاً أن المعونة دائماً غير بناءة.
Some aid may have built a hospital, fed a hungry village.
بعض المعونة قد تبني مستشفى، تُطعم قرية جائعة.
It may have built a road, and that road
يمكنها أن تُشيد طريقاً، وذلك الطريق
may have served a very good role.
ربما يخدم بدور جيّد للغاية.
The mistake of the international aid industry
إن خطأ قطاع المعونة الدولية
is to pick these isolated incidents of success,
هو اختيار هذه الحوادث المعزولة من النجاح ،
generalize them, pour billions and trillions of dollars into them,
تعميمهم، في ضخ مليارات الدولارات وترليونات الدولارات إليهم،
and then spread them across the whole world,
ومن ثم نشرها في أنحاء العالم،
ignoring the specific and unique circumstances in a given village,
تجاهل الظروف الخاصة والفريدة من نوعها في قرية معينة،
the skills, the practices, the norms and habits
المهارات، الممارسات، القواعد والعادات
that allowed that small aid project to succeed --
التي سمحت بمشروع المعونة الصغيرة للنجاح --
like in Sauri village, in Kenya, where Jeffrey Sachs is working --
مثل ساوري في قرية في كينيا، حيث تعمل جيفري ساجس --
and therefore generalize this experience
وبالتالي عمموا هذه التجربة
as the experience of everybody.
كتجربة لكل الناس.
Aid increases the resources available to governments,
المعونة تزيد المصادر المُتاحة للحكومات،
and that makes working in a government the most profitable thing
وهذا يجعل العمل في الحكومة هو أكثر شئ مربح
you can have, as a person in Africa seeking a career.
يمكنك أن تكون كشخص في أفريقيا يبحث عن عمل.
By increasing the political attractiveness of the state,
بزيادة السياسات الجاذبة للدولة،
especially in our ethnically fragmented societies in Africa,
وخاصة في مجتماعتنا المجزأة قبليا في أفريقيا،
aid tends to accentuate ethnic tensions
المعونة تؤدي إلى تعميق التوترات القبلية
as every single ethnic group now begins struggling to enter the state
باعتبار أن كل قبيلة تبدأ الآن تكافح من أجل الدخول إلى الدولة
in order to get access to the foreign aid pie.
من أجل الحصول على كعكة المساعدات الخارجية.
Ladies and gentlemen, the most enterprising people in Africa
سيداتي وسادتي، إن أكثر الأناس المقدامين في أفريقيا
cannot find opportunities to trade and to work in the private sector
لا يجدون فرص للتجارة والعمل في القطاع الخاص
because the institutional and policy environment is hostile to business.
ﻷن بيئة المؤسسية والسياسة معادية للعمل.
Governments are not changing it. Why?
الحكومات لا تتغير. لماذا؟
Because they don't need to talk to their own citizens.
ﻷنها لا تحتاج أن تتحدث إلى مواطنيها.
They talk to international donors.
إنها تتحدث إلى المانحيين الدوليين.
So, the most enterprising Africans end up going to work for government,
إذاً الأفارقة المقدامين في النهاية سيعملون من الحكومة،
and that has increased the political tensions in our countries
وذلك أدى لزيادة التوترات السياسية في بلداننا
precisely because we depend on aid.
بالتحديد ﻷننا نعتمد على المعونة.
I also want to say that it is important for us to
أريد أن أضيف أيضاَ أنه من المهم لنا أن
note that, over the last 50 years, Africa has been receiving increasing aid
نلحظ أن في السنوات ال 50 الماضية أفريقيا تستقبل زيادات في المعونة
from the international community,
من المجتمع الدولي
in the form of technical assistance, and financial aid,
في شكل مساعدة تقنية، ومعونة مالية،
and all other forms of aid.
وكل أنواع المعونة الأخرى.
Between 1960 and 2003, our continent received 600 billion dollars of aid,
بين عامين 1960 و2003 أستقبلت قارتنا 600 بليون دولار من المعونة
and we are still told that there is a lot of poverty in Africa.
وما زلنا نتحدث عن أن هنالك الكثير من الفقر في أفريقيا.
Where has all the aid gone?
أين ذهبت كل هذه المعونة؟
I want to use the example of my own country, called Uganda,
أريد أن أستخدم مثالاُ من موطني يوغندا
and the kind of structure of incentives that aid has brought there.
وهذا نوع هيكل الحوافز الذي جلب المعونة هناك.
In the 2006-2007 budget, expected revenue: 2.5 trillion shillings.
في حزمة 2006-،2007، الإيرادات المتوقعة 2ز5 ترليون شلن.
The expected foreign aid: 1.9 trillion.
المعونة الخارجية المتوقعة: 1.9 ترليون.
Uganda's recurrent expenditure -- by recurrent what do I mean?
نفقات أوغندا المتكررة -- بالمتكررة ماذا أعني؟
Hand-to-mouth is 2.6 trillion.
اليد إلى الفم -- 2.6 ترليون.
Why does the government of Uganda budget spend 110 percent
لماذا الحكومة اليوغندية تنفق 110 في المئة من ميزانيتها
of its own revenue?
من إيراداتها الذاتية؟
It's because there's somebody there called foreign aid, who contributes for it.
ذلك ﻷن هنالك أحداً يُدعى معونة خارجية يساهم لها.
But this shows you that the government of Uganda
ولكن هذا يظهر لكم أن حكومة يوغندا
is not committed to spending its own revenue
ليست ملتزمة بإنفاق إيراداتها الذاتية
to invest in productive investments,
للإستثمار في الإستثمارات المنتجة،
but rather it devotes this revenue
بل وتكرس هذه الإيرادات
to paying structure of public expenditure.
لدفع هيكل الإنفاق العام.
Public administration, which is largely patronage, takes 690 billion.
الإدارة العامة، التي هي محاباة الأقارب والأصدقاء، وتأخذ 690 مليار.
The military, 380 billion.
الجيش، 380 مليار دولار.
Agriculture, which employs 18 percent of our poverty-stricken citizens,
الزراعة، والتي توظف 18 في المئة من المواطنين الذين يعانون من الفقر ،
takes only 18 billion.
تأخذ فقط 18 بليون.
Trade and industry takes 43 billion.
التجارة والصناعة يأخذون 43 بليون.
And let me show you, what does public expenditure --
وأسمحوا لي أن أريكم النفقات العامة
rather, public administration expenditure -- in Uganda constitute?
أو بدلا عن ذلك، إدارة النفقات العامة -- في مؤسسة يوغندا؟
There you go. 70 cabinet ministers, 114 presidential advisers,
هناك تذهب. الوزراء 70، المستشارين الرئاسيين 114 --
by the way, who never see the president, except on television.
بالمناسبة، الذين لا يرون الرئيس، إلا على شاشة التلفزيون،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And when they see him physically, it is at public functions like this,
وعندما يروه فعلاً، إنها وظيفتهم الأساسية كالتالي،
and even there, it is him who advises them.
وحتى هناك، إنه هو الذي ينصحهم هُم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We have 81 units of local government.
لدينا 81 وحدات حكم محلي؛
Each local government is organized like the central government --
أي وحدة محلية منظمة كوحدة حكومية مركزية --
a bureaucracy, a cabinet, a parliament,
والبيروقراطية، وتشكيل الحكومة الجديدة في البرلمان ،
and so many jobs for the political hangers-on.
والكثير من فرص العمل للسياسيين الجوعى .
There were 56, and when our president wanted to
كانت هناك 56، وعندما يريد رئيسنا
amend the constitution and remove term limits,
تعديل الدستور وإزالة القيود على فترات،
he had to create 25 new districts, and now there are 81.
عليه إنشاء 25 وحدة جديدة، والآن هنالك 81.
Three hundred thirty-three members of parliament.
333 عضو في البرلمان.
You need Wembley Stadium to host our parliament.
نحتاج إلى أستاد ويمبلي لنستضيف برلماننا.
One hundred thirty-four commissions
134 لجنة
and semi-autonomous government bodies,
وأجسام حكومية شبه مستقلة،
all of which have directors and the cars. And the final thing,
ولها كلها مدراء وسيارات و-- والشيء الأخير،
this is addressed to Mr. Bono. In his work, he may help us on this.
وهذا موجّه للسيد بونو. في عمله ربما سيساعدنا في هذا.
A recent government of Uganda study found
وجدت الدراسة أن حكومة يوغندا الأخيرة
that there are 3,000 four-wheel drive motor vehicles
أن هنالك 3000 سيارة دفع رباعي
at the Minister of Health headquarters.
في مقر وزير الصحة.
Uganda has 961 sub-counties, each of them with a dispensary,
يوغندا لديها 961 مقاطعة فرعية، كل واحدة منهم لديها مستوصف،
none of which has an ambulance.
ولا واحد منها لديها إسعاف.
So, the four-wheel drive vehicles at the headquarters
إذا العربات الرباعية الدفع لدى الوزير
drive the ministers, the permanent secretaries, the bureaucrats
تقود الوزراء، والأمناء الدائمين، والبيروقراطيين
and the international aid bureaucrats who work in aid projects,
وبيروقراطيين الاغاثة الدولية الذين يعملون في مشروعات المعونة
while the poor die without ambulances and medicine.
في حين أن الفقراء يموتون دون اسعاف وادوية.
Finally, I want to say that before I came to speak here,
أخيرا ، أريد أن أقول إنه قبل أن أجئ ﻷتكلم هنا ،
I was told that the principle of TEDGlobal
أُخبرت بأن القواعد الأساسية لمؤتمر تيد العالمي
is that the good speech should be like a miniskirt.
بأن الكلام الجيّد يجب أن يكون كالتنورة القصيرة --
It should be short enough to arouse interest,
يجب أن يكون قصيراً كفاية ليجذب الإنتباه،
but long enough to cover the subject.
ولكن طويل كفاية ليغطي الموضوع.
I hope I have achieved that.
أرجو أن أكون قد حققت ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)